Finding Aid for Department of English Language and Literature (University of Michigan) records, 1919-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of English Language and Literature (University of Michigan) records
1919-1994
1960-1979
University of Michigan. Department of English Language and Literature.
87142 Bimu C26 2
Correspondence, topical files, photographs, and printed material relating to the operation and activities of the department, primarily after 1960 during the administrations of Warner Rice, Russell A. Fraser, John L. Styan, and Jay L. Robinson; also include scattered files before 1960 and after 1979.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
9.8 linear feet
The records were transferred from the Department of English Language and Literature (Donor No. 1802 ) in July 1990. Printed material is received at regular intervals.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open for research except for closed records located in Boxes 7 and 9.
The origin of the study of English language and literature at the University of Michigan can be traced to the 1840s. From 1841 to 1852 the university curriculum of traditional college courses included classes in both rhetoric and English grammar. A course in English composition was added in the academic year 1852/1853. The instruction in English and rhetoric was shared by professors from various disciplines.
English literature was first studied at the university following the appointment of Erastus Otis Haven in 1854 as professor of History and English Literature. Professor Haven resigned in 1856, and courses in English literature were suspended until the professorship was filled by Andrew Dickson White in 1857. White held the position until 1863. He later became the first president of Cornell University and ambassador to Germany. It was not until the appointment of Moses Coit Tyler in 1867 as professor of Rhetoric and English Literature and as the first chairman of the department that studies in English literature truly flourished.
Professor Tyler, who served as chairman until 1881, was one of the first and foremost scholars of American literature in the country. He authored a number of works on the subject, including The History of American Literature, 1607-1765 and The Literary History of the American Revolution. According to The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey:
His [Tyler's] desire was that students might 'come to know for themselves the exhilaration of original research.' By 'research' Tyler did not mean quite what we now understand by the word, nor what he himself practiced. His first hope was only to escape from 'the difficulty of interesting young people in critical estimates of books which they had never before seen or heard of.' Nevertheless, the assignment of readings in original sources led not only to the introduction in 1875 of the senior course announced as the Study of Masterpieces, but also to the offering of graduate seminars ... By 1881, when Tyler left for Cornell, the main course for future programs in English was set at the University of Michigan and also at other American universities, as the result largely of the pioneer work of Tyler. (Volume II, page 549)
Under Tyler, a course of study in English leading to the Bachelor of Letters degree was established in 1877/1878, which led to a twenty percent increase in the number of students enrolled in the department in the following year.
Under the chairmanship of Isaac Newton Demmon (1881 to 1920), the department experienced a period of steady growth. The number of English courses offered doubled by the turn of the century. Professor Demmon is perhaps best remembered for his work as editor of a number of university publications and for his acquisitions of important literary collections for the university, such as the McMillan Shakespeare Library. Fred Newton Scott was also very active in the department in the area of rhetoric. In 1890/1891, he taught the first college course in journalism in the country. He attracted gifted students to the department from all over the country, many of whom became well known in their field. In 1903, he became head of the Rhetoric Department upon its separation from the English Department. The new department continued the teaching of linguistics, composition, journalism, and creative writing. The two departments were reunited in 1930 and renamed the Department of English Language and Literature.
Under the leadership of Louis A. Strauss (chairman, 1920-1936) and Louis Ignatius Bredvold (chairman, 1936-1947), the number of both students and faculty continued to increase and professors became more specialized in their teaching and scholarship. The expansion of the department was reflected in the establishment of an executive committee in 1926. Prior to this time, the department had always met as a whole, but with the increase in faculty this was no longer possible. The first meeting of the executive committee took place on October 19, 1926, and consisted of the full professors in the department.
Among the most notable events which occurred during the Strauss/Bredvold years were the introduction of the Freshman Composition Program in 1930, the establishment of the Hopwood awards, and the commencement of the Dictionary Projects. The latter two activities continue to this day. The annual Jule and Avery Hopwood awards were first presented in 1930/1931 and were intended to encourage work in creative writing among students. The competitions are limited to students at the University of Michigan who are enrolled in at least one course in English composition. As early as 1931 publishers were interested in the results of the contests, and many winners have had their works published. Regarding the origin of the Hopwood awards The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey states:
No one knows when he [Avery Hopwood] conceived the highly dramatic idea that resulted in the Hopwood awards, but one may surmise that his own experience as a struggling young writer on the Michigan campus had something to do with his desire to make the path of the talented student an easier road to travel. Upon his death in 1928 he left one-fifth of his large fortune to his alma mater with the proviso that the income from the bequest should be given away each year 'to students ... who perform the best creative work in the fields of dramatic writing, fiction, poetry, and the essay.' (Volume II, page 573)
The project of editing the Early Modern English Dictionary, a dictionary of the English language as used from 1475 to 1700, began at the University of Michigan in 1927 under the direction of Professor Charles C. Fries. Its work was suspended during World War II and later resumed in 1966. In 1930, the Middle English Dictionary project, a dictionary of the English language as used from 1100 to 1475, was transferred from Cornell University to the University of Michigan so that the two dictionary projects might benefit each other. Publication of the Middle English Dictionary began in 1954. In the mid 1970s, responsibility for the Middle English Dictionary was transferred from the department to the Vice President for Research. (Work on the Early Modern English Dictionary was suspended; for more information the researcher should contact Professor Richard Bailey of the Department of English Language and Literature.)
The chairmanships of Warner Grenelle Rice and Russell A. Fraser were marked by the development of a number of specialized programs of study within the university in which interested faculty were encouraged to participate. The chairmanship of Professor Rice from 1947 to 1968 witnessed the introduction of the American Culture program, the Comparative Literature program, the Great Books program, and the university's first film courses. Professor Rice was also very active in administering the university libraries and served as director from 1941 to 1953. Professor Fraser (chairman, 1968-1973) was very supportive of research and scholarly activities of the faculty. As a result, faculty from the department were active on university committees which formed such programs as the Medieval and Renaissance Collegium and Women's Studies. In 1971, a new graduate program leading to the degree of Doctor of Arts in English was initiated. The program was designed to prepare teachers for two-year or community colleges and focused on teaching methods rather than research.
From 1973 to 1974, John L. Styan served a brief tenure as chairman; Jay L. Robinson was appointed Styan's successor in 1974. Professor Robinson was instrumental in acquiring funding for continued work on the dictionary projects and also for the creation of the English Composition Board (ECB). The ECB was created to oversee the composition requirement for students enrolled in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts and to foster effective writing among undergraduates. During Robinson's chairmanship renewed attention was given to student interests and the department began offering courses in such areas as popular culture and science fiction. In 1982, Ejner J. Jensen served as chairman for the first six months; John R. Knott took over the duties of the chairman in September. Under the chairmanship of Professor Knott, the Executive Committee dealt with such issues as graduate student recruitment and revising the department's salary policy. After years of planning, a program leading to the Master of Fine Arts in Creative Writing degree was instituted in 1983. Professor Knott was succeeded as chairman by Robert Weisbuch in 1987.
For additional information on the history of the department, the researcher should read the essays in The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, Volume II and Volume VI.
Chairmen of The Department of English
1867-1881 Moses Coit Tyler
1881-1920 Isaac Newton Demmon
1920-1938 Louis A. Strauss
1938-1947 Louis Ignatius Bredvold
1947-1968 Warner Grenelle Rice
1968-1973 Russell A. Fraser
1973-1974 John L. Styan
1974-1981 Jay L. Robinson
1982 Ejner J. Jensen
1982-1987 John R. Knott
1987-1994 Robert Weisbuch
1994- Martha J. Vicinus
The records of the Department of English Language and Literature measure 9.8 linear feet and date from 1919 to 1994. The bulk of the materials are from the years 1960 to 1979 and generally coincide with the chairmanships of Warner Rice, Russell Fraser, John Styan, and Jay Robinson. The records primarily document the internal workings of the department and its relationship with other units in the university. The majority of the records were created by the department itself and consist of minutes of committee and faculty meetings, correspondence, department reviews, course outlines, position requests, and newsletters and publications.
The records of the Department of English Language and Literature are divided into four series: Correspondence, Topical Files, Photographs, and Printed Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood Prizes.; Henry Russel Award (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; William L. Clements Library.; Inlander.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Campbell, Oscar James, 1879-1970.
Contributors:
Bredvold, Louis I. (Louis Ignatius), b. 1888.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; Campbell, Oscar James, 1879-1970.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Cowden, Roy William.; Fraser, Russell A.; Gessner, Robert, 1907-1968; Gingerich, Solomon Francis, 1875-; Griggs, Earl Leslie, 1899-; Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933.; Hutchins, Henry Clinton, b. 1889.; Jones, Howard Mumford, 1892-1980; Kuyper, George Adrian.; Moore, Samuel.; Rice, Warner Grenelle, 1899-; Robinson, Jay L., 1932-; Strauss, Louis Abraham, 1872-1938.; Styan, J. L.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1.2 linear feet) is divided into four subseries: General, College of Literature, Science and the Arts, Rackham School of Graduate Studies, and University Executive Officers. The General subseries is divided into two sequences: the first and largest sequence is arranged chronologically from 1919 to 1939, a period of great development for the department; the second sequence, arranged alphabetically, is comprised of one folder of miscellaneous correspondence from the years 1965 to 1977. The last three subseries contain correspondence between the department and a number of university officials from the years 1965 to 1982. Topics are routine in nature and include curriculum changes, budget requests, and hiring.
  - General
    - Chronological
      - 1919-1936, 12 folders (Box 1)
      - (letter from Van Wyck Brooks), 1939 (Box 1)
    - Alphabetical, 1965-1977 (Box 1)
  - College of Literature, Science and Arts
    - Chronological
      - 1965-1969, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Alphabetical
      - Carduner, Jean R. (Associate Dean) ), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - Carruth, Hayden K. (Associate Dean), 1970-1974; 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Frye, Billy E. (Acting Dean), 1974-1979; 7 folders (Box 1)
      - Galler, Bernard (Associate Dean for Long Range Planning), 1975-1979 (Box 1)
      - Haber, William (Dean), 1967-1970 (Box 1)
      - Holbrook, Robert S. (Associate Dean), 1978-1979 (Box 1)
      - Jackson, Marion E. (Assistant Dean), 1975 (Box 1)
      - Knott, John R. (Acting Dean), 1979-1981 (Box 1)
      - Krimm, S. (Associate Dean), 1973 (Box 1)
      - Ledbetter, Robert (Assistant to the Dean), 1977-1982 (Box 1)
      - Meeker, John (Assistant to the Dean), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - Morris, Charles G. (Associate Dean), 1972-1976 (Box 1)
      - Mueller, Eva (Associate Dean), 1974-1980; 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Rasmussen, Paul (Associate Dean), 1976-1982 (Box 1)
      - Rhodes, Frank H. T. (Dean), 1971-1974; 9 folders (Box 1)
      - Shaw, James (Assistant Dean), 1971 (Box 1)
      - Spradlin, Paul A., 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - Witke, Charles (Associate Dean), 1972-1974; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Rackham School of Graduate Studies
    - Durner, Dwight (Assistant to the Dean), 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Ellis, Wade (Associate Dean), 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Feingold, Eugene (Associate Dean), 1979-1982 (Box 2)
    - Groesbeck, Byron L. (Associate Dean), 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Hay, George (Dean), 1968-1973 (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Ralph (Associate Dean), 1971-1976; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Spurr, Stephen H. (Dean), 1965-1971 (Box 2)
    - Stokes, Donald E. (Dean), 1971-1974; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Varner, Nellie M. (Associate Dean), 1976 (Box 2)
  - University Executive Officers
    - Fleming, Robben W. (President), 1968-1976 (Box 2)
    - Kennedy, Richard (Vice President for State Relations), 1975 (Box 2)
    - Overberger, Charles (Vice President of Research), 1973 (Box 2)
    - Radock, Michael (Vice President of University Relations), 1966 (Box 2)
    - Smith, Allan F. (Vice President of Academic Affairs), 1965-1977 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (8.8 linear feet) is divided into two large subseries; Departmental Files and University files. Each is arranged alphabetically. The Departmental Files contain material which relate to the internal activities and functions of the department, and the University Files contain materials which reflect the department's role as a unit within the University of Michigan.
  - Departmental Files
    A large portion of the records in the Departmental Files was created by committees, most notably the Executive Committee and review committees. Of special interest are the minutes of the Executive Committee which date from 1920 to 1984 and are almost complete. Minutes for the years 1928, 1929, and 1974/1975 are missing. The Executive Committee materials include one bound volume of meeting minutes from 1920 to 1934 and a series of unbound minutes from 1926 to 1963. Although the years overlap, the bound volume should be used in conjunction with the unbound minutes because they do not always contain the same materials. Also, minutes of faculty meetings are found interfiled with the Executive Committee minutes as well as in the Faculty Meeting Minutes folders. Because the Executive Committee was not established until 1926, the minutes prior to that time are actually of faculty meetings.
    The Final Reports of the Review Committees of 1962, 1972, and 1977/1978 are especially valuable because they evaluate the strengths and weaknesses of the department and identify future goals. Other departmental committees which are well documented include the Freshman English Committee, the Graduate Administrative and Curriculum Committee, and the Introductory Composition Committee.
    In addition to meeting minutes, the folders "Salaries", "Budget", and "Committee Assignments" are good sources of information from which to examine the administrative history of the department. Information regarding curriculum offerings and requirements can be found in such folders as "Course Syllabi and Descriptions", "Doctor of Arts in English Program", and "Freshman English Program". The "Position Requests" document new areas of instruction developed by the department and faculty vacancies in existing fields.
    The Graduate Student Teaching Assistants (GSTA) folders contain fairly substantive material regarding the role and the requirements of the GSTA's and GSTA training workshop materials. The folders on the Graduate Employee Organization document the effects on the department of the 1975/76 strike of graduate students.
    The records on the Dictionary Projects are substantial but generally date from after the revival of the project in the mid 1960s. For printed works on the Dictionary Projects, the researcher should consult the Bentley Historical Library Printed Works catalog under the heading Michigan. University. Middle English Dictionary.
    Despite the multitude of folders regarding professional organizations in the Topical Files series, many of these contain limited materials and the department's role within a particular organization is not always well documented.
    - Academy of American Poets, 1968 (Box 2)
    - American Council on Education Internship Program, 1969-1971; 1977 (Box 2)
    - Association for Academic Evaluation, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Association of Departments of English, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Austin Warren Scholarship Program, 1971/2 (Box 2)
    - Awards
      - General, 1959-1979 (Box 2)
      - Hopwood Awards, 1932-1936 (Box 2)
    - Black Graduate Students, Funding, 1970/71 (Box 2)
    - Black Poetry Anthology, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Budget
      - 1969-1975, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Budget questionnaire, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Chairman, Duties of (Box 2)
    - Colloquium on Curriculum, Lower Division, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Committee Assignments, 1946-1980 (Box 2)
    - Committees
      - Black Graduate Student Assimilation, Committee on, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Black Graduate Student Recruitment Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - Black Literature, Committee on, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
      - Black Undergraduate Recruitment Committee, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Computer Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - Dictionaries, Administrative Committee on, 1972 (Box 2)
      - English 123 Modification Task Force, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee
        - Elections, 1969-1975 (Box 2)
        - Minutes
          - Undated (Box 2)
          - (bound), 1920 November-1934 July (Box 2)
          - 1926-1963 (36 folders, missing 1928 and 1929) (Box 2)
          - (22 folders, missing 1974/75), 1964-1980 (Box 3)
          - 1981-1984 June, 4 folders (Box 4)
        - Retreat Materials, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Freshman English Committee
        - General, 1970-1975; 4 folders (Box 4)
        - Survey, undated (Box 4)
      - Graduate Administrative and Curriculum Committee
        - 1970 (Box 4)
        - 1971-1974 (Box 4)
        - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
      - Graduation Requirements, Commission on, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Honors Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - Hopwood Committee, 1958-1979 (Box 4)
      - Introductory Composition Committee
        - General
          - 1973-1974 (Box 4)
          - 1979-1988, 9 folders (Box 4)
        - "Self Study of Departmental Courses Fulfilling the LSA Freshman Writing Requirement,", 1984 (Box 4)
        - Textbook Evaluations
          - 1983 (Box 4)
          - 1987 (Box 4)
      - Library Committee, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
      - Lower Division Courses Committee, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Promotion Policy Review Committee, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Professional Semester, Committee on, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Review Committees
        - Final Report, 1962 (Box 4)
        - 1972
          - Final Report (Box 4)
          - Hearing Minutes (Box 4)
          - Meeting Minutes, 1972 September-December (Box 4)
          - Questionnaire Responses from Peer Universities (Box 4)
          - Reports of Subcommittees (Box 4)
          - Response to Draft Report (Box 4)
          - Statements
            - Committees (Box 4)
            - Faculty (Box 4)
            - Graduate Students (Box 4)
            - Undergraduate Students (Box 4)
        - 1977-1978
          - Final Report (Box 5)
          - Minutes and Correspondence (Box 5)
          - Reports of Subcommittees (Box 5)
          - Review Response (Box 5)
        - 1979-1980
          - Doctor of Arts review committee (Box 5)
      - Scholarly Activities, Committee on, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
      - Teacher Preparation and Professional Relations, Committee on, 1965-1972 (Box 5)
      - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, 1969-1978 (Box 5)
      - Upper Division Courses, Committee on, 1968-1969; undated (Box 5)
      - Workload Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Composition Requirements, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Conferences
      - Conference for High School English Teachers, 1952-1967 (Box 5)
      - Conference on College Composition and Communication, 1963; 1969 (Box 5)
      - Doctor of Arts in English Conference, 1980 (Box 5)
      - Introductory Composition Conference, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Departmental Files
    The University Files subseries is smaller than the Departmental Files subseries and documents to a limited extent the department's interactions with other programs, committees, and departments of the university. The Medieval and Renaissance Collegium, the Humanities Department of the College of Engineering, and the Doctor of Education Program in English and Education contain program evaluations. The materials on the Department of Linguistics contain some early materials from the time of its formation in 1961.
    - Course Evaluations, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Course Mart, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - Course Numbering, 1956-1957 (Box 5)
    - Course Syllabi and Descriptions
      - Undated (Box 5)
      - 1965-1971 (Box 5)
      - Fall, 1975 (Box 5)
      - 1976
        - Winter (Box 5)
        - Fall (Box 5)
      - Winter, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Fall, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Winter, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Danforth Program, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Demmon, I.N. (Proposed Volume of Studies to be dedicated to; 1920) (Box 5)
    - Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst Program, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Development Grant, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Dictionary Projects
      - General, 1965-1968; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Concordances
        - Crawford, undated (Box 5)
        - Jonson, 1933; 1965-1968 (Box 5)
      - Early Modern English Dictionary
        - 1928 (Box 5)
        - 1971-1972 (Box 5)
        - 1974-1976, 1978 (Box 5)
      - "Instructions for Excerptors", 1975; undated (Box 5)
      - Middle English Dictionary
        - 1971-1973 (Box 5)
        - Report, 1974 (Box 5)
        - 1975 (Box 5)
        - Review, 1977 (Box 5)
        - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Doctor of Arts in English Program, 1970-1981 (Box 5)
    - Endowed Fellowships, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - English Composition Board, 1975-1979 (Box 6)